<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="chap4">
  <title>Supported Systems</title>

  <subtitle>Supported UNIX-like OSes</subtitle>

  <para>OpenNMS is written almost entirely in Java, and should be able to run
  on any system that suuports the Java 1.4 Virtual Machine. There are
  requirements for other programs such as PostgreSQL, Perl, RRDTool and
  Tomcat4, but the 1.4 JDK is the key requirement (as most of the other
  packages can be compiled from source).</para>

  <para>The following are the systems that support or are known to run
  OpenNMS.</para>

  <sect1 id="chap4sect1">
    <title>Fully Supported</title>

    <para>The following Linux distributions and other unix-like systems are
    supported out-of-the-box with native installation packages.</para>

    <bridgehead>Red Hat Linux 7.x, Red Hat Linux 8, Red Hat Linux 9 and Red
    Hat Enterprise Linux 3</bridgehead>

    <para>PostgreSQL 7.2 and later has shipped with Red Hat Linux since
    version 7.3. Be sure to follow the above instructions.</para>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Fedora Core 1, Fedora Core 2 and Fedora Core 3.</title>

      <para>OpenNMS is known to build and run on Fedora Core 1, Fedora Core 2
      and Fedora Core 3.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Debian Woody on Intel</title>

      <para>Debian packages should be available on ftp.opennms.org, and at the
      following apt-repository:<programlisting>deb http://debian.opennms.org/apt debian/opennms stable</programlisting></para>
    </formalpara>

    <para>Special Tomcat 4.1 packages were created, since only 4.0 is
    supported in stable. For instructions see this <ulink
    url="http://opennms.netstatz.com/Debian_ONMS_HOWTO.html#toc2">How-To</ulink>
    written by Ian MacDonald.</para>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Solaris 8 and Solaris 9 on x86 and SPARC</title>

      <para>Packages are available at ftp.opennms.org for Solaris 8 and
      Solaris 9 running on SPARC and Solaris 9 running on x86.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Mandrake 8, Mandrake 9 and Mandrake 10</title>

      <para>Please note that while we build packages for Mandrake 8.x, we do
      not do any formal testing on it. Packages are provided as a
      convenience.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title>SuSE 8 and SuSE 9</title>

      <para>OpenNMS is known to build and run on SuSE.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title>MacOSX 10.3</title>

      <para>On MacOSX, the Fink distribution packages of OpenNMS are
      supported. See <ulink url="http://fink.sf.net/">the Fink web
      site</ulink> for more information on installing and using Fink.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <para>Also note that on MacOSX, PostgreSQL must be configured in the same
    manner as above for Linux. <emphasis>However</emphasis>, to do so you will
    need to update the SHM settings so that the OS allows enough resources for
    PostgreSQL to run with larger buffers.</para>

    <para>To do so, you must edit
    <emphasis>/System/Library/StartupItems/SystemTuning/SystemTuning</emphasis>
    so that the sysctl lines look like so (at a minimum): <programlisting> sysctl -w kern.sysv.shmmax=16777216 sysctl -w
      kern.sysv.shmmin=1 sysctl -w kern.sysv.shmmni=128 sysctl -w
      kern.sysv.shmseg=32 sysctl -w kern.sysv.shmall=4096 </programlisting></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="chap4sect2">
    <title>Unsupported</title>

    <para>The following UNIX systems are unsupported, but have been known to
    work.</para>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Debian Woody on SPARC</title>

      <para>OpenNMS is known to run on Debian on SPARC</para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Red Hat 6.2</title>

      <para>No special cases known.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Solaris 7</title>

      <para>There have been reports of OpenNMS building and running on Solaris
      on the discuss list.</para>
    </formalpara>
  </sect1>
</chapter>