<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="chap4" label="4.">
	<title>Supported Systems</title>
	<subtitle>Supported UNIX-like OSes</subtitle>
	<para>
		The following are the systems that OpenNMS is supported or known to run on.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="chap4sect1" label="4.1.">
		<title>Fully Supported</title>
		<para>
			The following Linux distributions are supported out-of-the-box with
			native installation packages.
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>RedHat 7.x</title>
					<para>
						On RedHat 7.2 and up, it is suggested that you use the
						official RedHat PostgreSQL RPMs that come with
						your distribution.  However, for OpenNMS to work
						correctly, you will need to make sure that tcp
						sockets are enabled.  It is also suggested that
						you increase the maximum number of connections
						and buffers.
					</para>
				</formalpara>
				<para>
					To do so, start postgresql with the command
					'<emphasis>service postgresql start</emphasis>'
					(to make sure that PostgreSQL's init has created
					your data directory), and then edit the file
					'<emphasis>/var/lib/pgsql/data/postgresql.conf</emphasis>'
					and make sure it has the following lines:
<programlisting>
		tcpip_socket = true
		max_connections = 256
		shared_buffers = 1024
</programlisting>

					Then run '<emphasis>service postgresql restart</emphasis>'
					to restart with the new configuration.
				</para>
				<para>
					If you do use the PostgreSQL RPMs provided with OpenNMS,
					you will need the <emphasis>readline41</emphasis>
					compatibility RPM installed, because our RPMs were built
					against RedHat 7.0.  You can get it off your RedHat 7.2 CD,
					or at <ulink url="ftp://ftp.redhat.com/pub/redhat/linux/7.2/en/os/i386/RedHat/RPMS/readline41-4.1-10.i386.rpm">RedHat's
					FTP site</ulink>.
				</para>
				<para>
					Note that if you use the "lynx installer", these options
					will automatically be added for you, and postgresql will
					be restarted.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>Mandrake 8.x</title>
					<para>
						Please note that while we build packages for Mandrake
						8.x, we do not do any formal testing on it.  Packages
						are provided as a convenience.
					</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap4sect2" label="4.2.">
		<title>Unsupported</title>
		<para>
			The following UNIX systems are unsupported, but have been known to
			work.
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>RedHat 6.2</title>
					<para>
						No special cases known.
					</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>Solaris 7 and 8</title>
					<para>
						There have been reports of OpenNMS building and
						running on Solaris on the discuss list.
					</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>Debian Woody</title>
					<para>
						Debian packages for OpenNMS are in-progress, and are
						expected to work before a 1.0 release of OpenNMS.
					</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>MacOS X</title>
					<para>
						OpenNMS is known to build and run on OSX.
					</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
