<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="chap2" label="2.">
	<title>What's New?</title>
	<subtitle>Changes in This OpenNMS</subtitle>
	<para>
		Besides bugfixes, there are a large number of UI, as well as behind-the-scene, changes in
		OpenNMS 1.0.0 and above.
	</para>
        <sect1 id="chap2sect1" label="2.1.">
                <title>Changes in OpenNMS 1.0.2 and Above</title>
                <para>
                        The following bug fixes and configuration additions occurred between 1.0.0 and 1.0.2:
                        <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                        <formalpara>
                                                <title>Corrected Event Configuration Functionality</title>
                                                <para>
                                                        The SNMP Generic Traps, numbers 0 through 5, were
							hard-coded into OpenNMS. Thus if you wanted to
							treat linkDown events from one system differently
							than another, you had to do so via an external script.
							This has been corrected. Also, the order in which
							the events are listed in eventconf.xml is now strictly
							enforced. Bug 666
                                                </para>
                                        </formalpara>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <formalpara>
                                                <title>Added Over 2750 Event Definitions</title>
                                                <para>
                                                        The eventconf.xml file has been greatly expanded to
                                                        include event definitions for SNMP traps from
                                                        3Com, APC, Brocade, Compaq Insight Manager, Cisco
                                                        Fore, HP, Intel, Microsoft, Novell, Oracle, SonicWall
                                                        and Xerox devices.
                                                </para>
                                        </formalpara>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <formalpara>
                                                <title>Notification Filtering Now Works Correctly</title>
                                                <para>
							The ability to build rules to filter notifications
							is one of the more useful features of notifications,
							but it didn't work. This has been corrected, and in
							the process, filtering node-level events via IP address
							was implemented. Bug 664.
                                                </para>
                                        </formalpara>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <formalpara>
                                                <title>Fixed Service Deletion in Downtime Model</title>
                                                <para>
							The poller downtime model allows for a service to be
							deleted if it has been down for a certain amount of
							time. This did not work correctly and has been fixed.
                                                </para>
                                        </formalpara>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <formalpara>
                                                <title>Reduced the Amount of Data Initially Collected from the ifTable</title>
                                                <para>
                                                        During discovery, the ifTable is collected from each device
							that is found to support SNMP. On some HP switches, this
							would fail due to a limitation on the SNMP maximum packet size.
							All non-essential ifTable elements were removed from the request
							that appears to resolve the problem.
                                                </para>
                                        </formalpara>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <formalpara>
                                                <title>Removed Spaces in Notification Path Names</title>
                                                <para>
                                                        Spaces in Notification Path names have been known to
							cause problems. The Web UI was modified to disallow
							spaces in path names. Bug 657.
                                                </para>
                                        </formalpara>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <formalpara>
                                                <title>Fixed the AM/PM Ordering on Performance Report UI.</title>
                                                <para>
							In the Custom Performance Report Web UI, 11 PM was
							followed by 12 PM, when it should have been 12 AM. This
							has been corrected. Bug 515.
                                                </para>
                                        </formalpara>
                                </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                </para>
	</sect1>
        <sect1 id="chap2sect2" label="2.2.">
                <title>Changes in OpenNMS 1.0.1 and Above</title>
                <para>
                        The following changes occurred between 1.0.0 and 1.0.1:
                        <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                        <formalpara>
                                                <title>Added a "contrib" Directory</title>
                                                <para>
							The "contrib" directory now contains code, such as nifty
							utilities, that exists outside of the main OpenNMS source
							but may prove useful. One such example is Tomas Carlsson's
							"mib2opennms" program. These programs are not supported.
                                                </para>
                                        </formalpara>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <formalpara>
                                                <title>Removed Duplicate Entries in <filename>capsd-configuration.xml</filename></title>
                                                <para>
							Both LDAP and Citrix protocol plug-ins were listed twice. This
							would slow down the capabilities scan considerably.	
                                                </para>
                                        </formalpara>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <formalpara>
                                                <title>Updated Data Collection and Graphing</title>
                                                <para>
							Added new entries to <filename>datacollection-config.xml</filename>
							and <filename>snmp-graph.properties</filename>.
                                                </para>
                                        </formalpara>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                        <formalpara>
                                                <title>Bugfixes</title>
                                                <para>
                                                        Many bugfixes, including allowing Threshold events to generate
							notifications, AdminStatus and OperStatus values causing
							exceptions, and rescans with certain devices.
                                                </para>
                                        </formalpara>
                                </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                </para>
        </sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect2" label="2.3.">
		<title>Changes in OpenNMS 1.0.0 and Above</title>
		<para>
			The following major changes occurred between 0.9.9 and 1.0.0:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<formalpara>
						<title>OpenSSH service is now "SSH"</title>
						<para>
							The OpenSSH service has been renamed to "SSH" and changed
							to detect common versions of SSH servers other than OpenSSH.
							Upgrades will retain the "OpenSSH" service as well for
							the sake of reports.
						</para>
					</formalpara>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<formalpara>
						<title>"Service Unresponsive" support</title>
						<para>
							There is now the possibility of having a state between
							"up" and "down" that flags a service as being unresponsive.
							This state can be reached when the service's port can be
							connected to, but it doesn't respond in a reasonable amount
							of time.
						</para>
					</formalpara>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<formalpara>
						<title>Bugfixes</title>
						<para>
							Many small bugfixes, including the "Calculating..." problem
							if RTC hasn't come up yet when tomcat starts.
						</para>
					</formalpara>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
