<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="chap1" label="1">
	<title>Chapter 1</title>
	<subtitle>OpenNMS Basics</subtitle>
                <para>
                        Warning: This document is deprecated and refers to old code. 
                        A new document is being developed, but for now the best source 
                        of information can be found on 
                        <ulink url="http://www.opennms.org/">The OpenNMS Wiki</ulink>.
                        This document may be wrong on a number of important issues, and it
                        will definitely waste your time.
                </para>

	<para>
		<emphasis>OpenNMS is a service and network management platform
		for automatic node discovery, network services monitoring, operator
		notification of problems, events consolidation, automatic action
		launching and service level performance monitoring.
		</emphasis>
	</para>
	<sect1 id="chap1sect1" label="1.1">
		<title>This guide</title>
		<para>
		This guide covers the use of the web UI on an already configured 
		management station.  It covers, finding information, 
		recognizing and acknowledging events and notices, as well as 
		reporting features, and asset management.  This guide is intended 
		for end users to be able to understand the current state of the managed 
		network, as well as research historical data, and make the most of 
		all the information available through the web interface.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap1sect2" label="1.2">
		<title>Terms used in this document</title>
		<para>
		The following is a list of terms relevant to this document.  Some of 
		these terms are used rather loosely within the industry, but are 
		defined here as they specifically apply to OpenNMS.
		</para>
		<formalpara><title>Interface</title>
		<para>Any logical IP address bound to a device that responds 
		to network requests, OR, anything reported via SNMP as being an interface.
		</para></formalpara>
		<formalpara><title>Service</title>
		<para>Any single, predefined network service that is bound to an interface.
		</para></formalpara>
		<formalpara><title>Node</title>
		<para>Any physical device with one or more interfaces.  A node may have multiple 
		interfaces, and may also have multiple services per interface.  (Whether or not 
		a specific interface "belongs" to a node can be determined using several different 
		methods i.e. SNMP or NetBIOS Names.  However, if no parenting information is 
		available for a given interface, it will be represented as a separate node.)
		</para></formalpara>
		<formalpara><title>Event</title>
		<para>Any significant occurrence or happening.
		</para></formalpara>
		<formalpara><title>Outage</title>
		<para>A temporary suspension of operation, signified by an inability to 
		communicate with a managed service. (a failed poll)
		</para></formalpara>
		<formalpara><title>Notice</title>
		<para>A notice is generated when specific events occur.  The notification process 
		usually consists of making users, or groups of users aware of these events via 
		email, pagers or other means, or in some cases initiating corrective actions.
		</para></formalpara>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
