<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="chap9" label="9">
	<title>Chapter 9</title>
	<subtitle>Summary</subtitle>
	<para>
	This project is always under development.  Features and functionality are 
	constantly being added or improved.  Some items in this documentation may from 
	time to time be out dated, or even refer to features that are not in the current 
	release of the software, and may only exist in the unstable branch of the CVS 
	reporitory.  There are a number of places to get help and information about 
	OpenNMS.  You may also wish to contribute code to the project.  In the following 
	section I will point out some resources that may be of use.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="chap9sect1" label="9.1">
		<title>Documentation</title>
		<para>
		In addition to this document there are also guides that cover installation, 
		and administration of OpenNMS.  The latest versions of these guides are usually 
		available from CVS.  While it is nearly impossible to document every aspect 
		of the project this way it is a very good place to start.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap9sect2" label="9.2">
		<title>Web Site</title>
		<para>
		The OpenNMS web site is available at
		<programlisting>
		http://www.opennms.org/
		</programlisting>
		From here you can gain access to the software, documentation, bug information, 
		mailing list archives, and CVS, as well as a number of other resources.
		</para>
	</sect1>
        <sect1 id="chap9sect3" label="9.3">
                <title>Email</title>
                <para>
                OpenNMS currently supports a number of mailing lists.  For more information 
		on specific lists and how to join, please visit
                <programlisting>
                http://www.opennms.org/index.php/Mailing_lists
                </programlisting>
                </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="chap9sect4" label="9.4">
                <title>Usenet News</title>
                <para>
                While as of the writing of this document OpenNMS does not host a specific 
		news group, you can often find information scattered around various other 
		news groups.
                </para>
        </sect1>
</chapter>
