<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="chap2" label="2">
<title>Chapter 2</title>
<subtitle>Configuration Files</subtitle>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect1" label="2.1">
		<title>actiond-configuration.xml</title>
		<para>
		Actions are external programs called based on events.  This file controls 
		the number of concurrent actions allowed as well as a time out for waiting 
		on a return.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect2" label="2.2">
		<title>AvailabilityReports.xsl SVGAvailReport.xsl PDFAvailReport.xsl</title>
		<para>
		These 3 files contain information for converting availability reports to PDF 
		format.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect3" label="2.3">
		<title>viewsdisplay.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines layout of categories for display in the web UI.  The actual
		categories are defined in the views.xml file.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect4" label="2.4">
		<title>views.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines view categories, and  services, to include per category as 
		well as thresholds.  These values are used by various components of OpenNMS 
		such as RTC, the availability report generator and the web UI.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect5" label="2.5">
		<title>capsd-configuration.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines capabilities (services) to be checked for on nodes discovered 
		either by the discovery daemon or via SNMP.   It aslo specifies which addresses, 
		and address ranges, that if discovered, should be managed or unmanaged.  
		It also provides for a default state or "management-policy" that covers addresses 
		not specifically referenced.
		</para>
		<programlisting>
		&lt;capsd-configuration rescan-frequency="86400000"
			management-policy="unmanaged"&gt;
		</programlisting>
		<para>
		Finally you can set the "rescan-frequency" which controls how often devices are rescaned 
		or rechecked for which services they provide.  This number, specified in milliseconds, 
		is used to determine how often items should get rescanned.  The default value is 86400000 
		or 24hrs.  
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect6" label="2.6">
		<title>controller-configuration.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines listeners for broadcast control JMS messages.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect7" label="2.7">
		<title>service-configuration.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines opennms services to start.  This is VM specific and controls which 
		services are started in which VMs
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect8" label="2.8">
		<title>create.sql database-schema.xml</title>
		<para>
		The file create.sql is the template for creating OpenNMS database.  It is typically 
		used by the install.pl script during the install process.  It is commented rather well.  
		The database-schema.xml defines the same database, in xml format, and is used by 
		the filtering system to format database queries
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect9" label="2.9">
		<title>datacollection-config.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file contains data collection information for RRDTool
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect10" label="2.10">
		<title>notifications.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines which events or UEIs warrant notification and a destination path for 
		said notification.
		</para>
		<programlisting>
		&lt;notification name="nodeAdded"&gt;
			&lt;uei&gt;&lt;![CDATA[http://uei.opennms.org/products/bluebird/nodes/nodeAdded]]&gt;&lt;/uei&gt;
			&lt;rule&gt;&lt;![CDATA[IPADDR IPLIKE *.*.*.*]]&gt;&lt;/rule&gt;
			&lt;destinationPath&gt;Email-Network/Systems&lt;/destinationPath&gt;
			&lt;text-message&gt;OpenNMS has discovered a new node named %parm[nodelabel]%.    Please be advised.&lt;/text-message&gt;
			&lt;subject&gt;%parm[nodelabel]% discovered.&lt;/subject&gt;
		&lt;/notification&gt;
		</programlisting>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect11" label="2.11">
		<title>destinationPaths.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file contains definitions for destination paths ie. whom to notify and by what method 
		either pager, email or email-pager.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect12" label="2.12">
		<title>notificationCommands.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines how to accomplish various contact methods defined in destinationPaths.xml.  
		This would include the location of executable and aliases for each type of contact along with 
		any other information needed to send information of the specific type.
		</para>
		<programlisting>
		&lt;command type="email"&gt;
			&lt;name&gt;/bin/mail&lt;/name&gt;
			&lt;lookup&gt;email&lt;/lookup&gt;
			&lt;lookup&gt;mail&lt;/lookup&gt;
			&lt;comment&gt;for sending email notifications&lt;/comment&gt;
			&lt;argument streamed="false"&gt;
				&lt;substitution&gt;-s&lt;/substitution&gt;
				&lt;switch&gt;-subject&lt;/switch&gt;
			&lt;/argument&gt;
			&lt;argument streamed="false"&gt;
				&lt;switch&gt;-email&lt;/switch&gt;
			&lt;/argument&gt;
			&lt;argument streamed="true"&gt;
				&lt;switch&gt;-tm&lt;/switch&gt;
			&lt;/argument&gt;
		&lt;/command&gt;
		</programlisting>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect13" label="2.13">
		<title>discovery-configuration.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines the ranges of addresses to discover, (ping sweep) as well as time outs, 
		number of retries, and number of threads to dedicate to discovery.  This file also provides 
		initial-sleep-time and restart-sleep-time.  These values are in miliseconds and control 
		how long after OpenNMS is started, that discovery should begin it's initial pass through 
		the addresses, and how long to wait between each additional pass.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect14" label="2.14">
		<title>eventconf.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines the Universal Event Identifiers or UEIs as well as their event masks, 
		descriptions, log messages, and severity levels.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect15" label="2.15">
		<title>eventd-configuration.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines operating parameters for eventd such as time outs and number of 
		listener threads.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect16" label="2.16">
		<title>users.xml / groups.xml</title>
		<para>
		These files hold information about users, and their contact information, as well as 
		groups and membership.  Information in these files is used for authentication on 
		the web UI as well as for contact methods needed by notifications.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect17" label="2.17">
		<title>log4j.properties</title>
		<para>
		This file defines properties for log4j.  It controls log size, rotation as well as 
		logging levels for individual category.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect18" label="2.18">
		<title>magic-users.properties</title>
		<para>
		This file includes special users, and takes precedence over users.xml for the users 
		that it has information about.  This is used internally to control permissions for 
		certain functions that interact with the web UI.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect19" label="2.19">
		<title>opennms-database.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines database type, name, authentication and mapping template to use for OpenNMS.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect20" label="2.20">
		<title>opennms-mapping.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file is empty but required by DTD for opennms-database.xml
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect21" label="2.21">
		<title>opennms-jms.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines properties for OpenJMS.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect22" label="2.22">
		<title>outage-configuration.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file simply defines number of writer threads allowed by the outage manager
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect23" label="2.23">
		<title>poller-configuration.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file is used to define packages as well as set up the various pollers.  A 
		package includes several items such as address ranges, services, outage calendars, 
		and down time models.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect24" label="2.24">
		<title>rrdtool-graph.properties</title>
		<para>
		This file is used to define RRD configurations for generating reports.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect25" label="2.25">
		<title>rtc-configuration.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines properties for RTC (Real Time Console) such as the rolling window 
		used to calculate percentages of down time, web UI refresh interval and how often 
		RTC sends updates to the web interface.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect26" label="2.26">
		<title>snmp-config.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file is used to define community strings for addresses or address ranges, one 
		snmp-config entry per community
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap2sect27" label="2.27">
		<title>trapd-configuration.xml</title>
		<para>
		This file defines the SNMP trap port
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
