<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="overview">
	<title>Overview</title>

	<section id="about-opennms">
		<title>About OpenNMS</title>

		<para>
			OpenNMS is the world's first enterprise-grade network management
			system developed under the open source model. As with any complex and
			powerful system, getting it installed and configured can take a
			little effort. It is the purpose of this document to explain what is
			required to get OpenNMS installed.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="how-to-use">
		<title>How to Use This Document</title>

		<para>So, how should you use this document? It is arranged in the
			following sections:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>This overview</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
					The programs on which OpenNMS depends, and how they need to
					be modified
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
					Installation and upgrade instructions, including details for
					specific operating systems and distributions
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
					Getting started with OpenNMS, including initial configuration
					and logging into the web interface
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Building OpenNMS from source</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Troubleshooting and Where to Get Help</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
			This installation guide relies strongly on the idea of "packages."
			Most modern operating systems and distributions have a system where
			software can be installed and managed through the use of packages
			that group the files belonging to a given application together (as well as
			managing changes to those files, removal, upgrades, etc.).
		</para>

		<para>
			Please see the latest
			<ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/docman/?group_id=4141">release notes</ulink>
			to see if your operating system is supported.  Currently, OpenNMS runs
			on many Linux distributions, Solaris, Mac OS X and Windows.
		</para>

		<para>
			This guide assumes that if you use packages, you do so consistently.
			This is because OpenNMS will attempt to determine if the software it
			requires is installed by using the operating system's built in
			package management system. If you've installed, say, Java, but not via packages,
			OpenNMS will be unable to determine that Java is installed and it
			will fail.
		</para>

		<para>
			To get back to the original question of "how should you use this
			document," first go through the second section to insure that you have all
			of the prerequisite applications properly installed and configured. Use
			the third section to help get those packages installed for your
			particular operating system, as well as the OpenNMS software. Finally, use
			the last section to help correct any errors your might encounter.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="minimum-requirements">
		<title>Minimum Requirements</title>

		<para>
			While it is impossible to exactly size OpenNMS for a particular environment,
			the following represents the minimum requirements for installation, assuming a
			network of about 200 devices. Note that OpenNMS can monitor more than 100 times
			that given the proper hardware.
		</para>

		<glosslist>
			<glossentry>
				<glossterm>Processor</glossterm>

				<glossdef>
					<para>A 1 GHz Pentium III (or equivalent processor) or better.
						OpenNMS can also take advantage of multiple processors.</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>

			<glossentry>
				<glossterm>Memory</glossterm>

				<glossdef>
					<para>
						A minimum of 256 MB of RAM, although 512 MB is strongly
						recommended. The OpenNMS Java Virtual Machine benefits from large
						amounts of memory, up to 2 GB, and more if using a 64-bit processor.
					</para>
					<para>
						Given a budget choice between more RAM and a faster CPU, choose
						more RAM.
					</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>

			<glossentry>
				<glossterm>Disk Space</glossterm>

				<glossdef>
					<para>
						OpenNMS requires about 200 MB of disk space for the program
						files. In addition, each data variable collected requires, by
						default, a little under 300 KB of disk space.  It is safe to assume
						that each interface being managed will require around 2 MB of disk
						space, so for 200 interfaces you are looking at 400 MB (conservatively).
						Depending on the number of events stored, you can assume 100 MB to
						200 MB are required for the database. Finally, the OpenNMS logs
						can grow quite large, especially in debug mode.
					</para>
					<para>
						Edit the <filename>log4j.properties</filename> file in the OpenNMS
						configuration directory (usually <filename>/opt/opennms/etc</filename>
						or <filename>/etc/opennms</filename>) to change those settings.  By
						default, the Log4J file rotation is configured to use 100MB per log
						file, which ends up using a little under 2 GB.
					</para>

					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: Due to the write-heavy nature of
						time-series data and the database, it is recommended that you do not use
						RAID-5 with OpenNMS. RAID-1 or RAID-1+0 is recommended if using RAID.
						In addition, LVM adds a small but appreciable amount of overhead and it
						is recommended that you do not use it.
					</para>
				</glossdef>
			</glossentry>
		</glosslist>
	</section>
</chapter>