<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="troubleshooting">
  <title>Troubleshooting an OpenNMS Installation</title>

  <section id="common-installation-issues">
    <title>Common Installation Issues</title>

    <para>The following section contains advice for overcoming common
    installation issues. If your issue is not addressed below, please see the
    section on where to get help.</para>

    <section id="dependency-problems">
      <title>Dependency Problems</title>

      <para>To assist with code management, the easiest way to install OpenNMS
      is via packages. Every effort has been made to insure that the packages
      OpenNMS depends on are required before the OpenNMS package can be
      installed. You should be able to find those packages on the distribution
      CDs that came with your system. For some of the more obscure packages,
      you can visit the OpenNMS <ulink url="ftp://ftp.opennms.org">FTP</ulink>
      site and check in the <filename>/pub/dependencies</filename> directory.
      In addition, sites like <ulink
      url="http://distro.ibiblio.org/">Ibiblio</ulink> and <ulink
      url="http://www.freshrpms.net">FreshRPMs</ulink> are also good
      sources.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="not-finished-starting-up">
      <title>Error: "Started OpenNMS, but it has not finished starting
      up"</title>

      <para>This can happen for a a number of reasons. You can run
      "<code>opennms -v status</code>" a few times after getting this error to
      see if OpenNMS eventually starts itself completely and if not, to see
      which daemons never start up completely. Here are some of the likely
      causes of this problem:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>OpenNMS takes a while to startup. This can happen on larger
          installations and when this happens "<code>opennms -v status</code>"
          will eventually show that all services have started up. By default,
          the startup script will try 10 times to see if OpenNMS has started
          and will wait 5 seconds between each try. You can increase the
          number of times by creating
          <filename>$OPENNMS_HOME/etc/opennms.conf</filename> and adding a
          line like "<code>START_TIMEOUT=20</code>" to double the number of
          times it tests. You can set the value to <code>0</code> to have the
          startup script not wait for OpenNMS to start.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Database is not running. If only about half or less of the
          daemons are shown as running, you can check for this condition by
          looking for <code>FATAL</code> errors in the log files. You'll see
          something like "<code>Error accessing database</code>" in the
          logs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Dhcpd doesn't start. See the item in the next section.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>JNI library problem. OpenNMS uses a few native C libraries
          that are accessed using JNI (Java Native Interface). Normally they
          just work, except users have started seeing problems when running
          Linux in native AMD64 mode where they end up using a 32-bit (x86)
          version of Java and a 64-bit (AMD64) version of the JNI libraries,
          or vice-versa. If you have this problem, you might want to try
          switching your version of Java from 32-bit to 64-bit or in the other
          direction.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Other. If the OpenNMS is installed, and the packages were not
          forced in using options like "<code>--nodeps</code>", the
          application should run just fine. If not, OpenNMS has a robust
          logging facility. Change to the logs directory (usually
          <filename>/var/log/opennms</filename>) and search the logs, using
          <filename>grep</filename> or your tool of choice, for words like
          <code>FATAL</code> and <code>ERROR</code> (the two highest log
          severities). Those events should give you clues as to why OpenNMS is
          not working.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="dhcp-poller-wont-start">
      <title>DHCP Poller Won't Start</title>

      <para>The OpenNMS DHCP poller will fail to start most operating systems
      (Linux, in particular) if you are running a DHCP client on the OpenNMS
      server. You'll see this by running "<code>opennms -v status</code>" and
      seeing everything in the <code>running</code> state, except for
      <code>Dhcpd</code>. The solution is to edit
      <filename>$OPENNMS_HOME/etc/service-configuration.xml</filename> and
      comment-out the "<code>&lt;service&gt;...&lt;/service&gt;</code>" stanza
      for <code>Dhcpd</code>. For example, this is what the section would look
      like after modification to disable <code>Dhcpd</code>:</para>

      <programlisting>        &lt;!-- Commented out since we have a DHCP client on this server
        &lt;service&gt;
                &lt;name&gt;OpenNMS:Name=Dhcpd&lt;/name&gt;
                &lt;class-name&gt;org.opennms.netmgt.dhcpd.jmx.Dhcpd&lt;/class-name&gt;
                &lt;invoke pass="1" method="start"/&gt;
                &lt;invoke at="status" pass="0" method="status"/&gt;
                &lt;invoke at="stop" pass="0" method="stop"/&gt;
        &lt;/service&gt;
        --&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>We discourage the running of OpenNMS on a server that is a DHCP
      client, both because OpenNMS may not be able to monitor DHCP servers on
      the network, and it is important that the monitoring server have a
      static IP address for receiving traps and to be reliant on as few
      network services as possible.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="runjava-could-not-find-jre">
      <title>Error: "runjava: Could not find an appropriate JRE"</title>

      <para>The <code><filename>runjava</filename></code> program is used to
      locate a suitable JRE for OpenNMS at install time that will be used for
      the installer and also for running OpenNMS after installation. See the
      section earlier in this manual on installing Java for OpenNMS. If you
      installed Java in a location that <code>runjava</code> cannot find, you
      can use its "<code>-f</code>" option to specify the JRE you want OpenNMS
      to use.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="database-errors-not-in-english">
      <title>Error: "The database server's error messages are not in English
      ..."</title>

      <para>You either need to set "<code>lc_messages = 'C'</code>" in your
      postgresql.conf file and restart PostgreSQL or upgrade to PostgreSQL 7.4
      or later.</para>

      <para>The installer does not always verify that an operation will
      succeed before executing the operation (e.g.: dropping database
      functions). In this case, it catches the exceptions returned from the
      database and checks the exception to see if it is an "okay" exception
      that should be ignored (e.g.: if the database function does not exist
      when attempting to drop a function).</para>

      <para>In PostgreSQL 7.4 and later, a new client/server protocol is used
      (version 3, to be specific) that provides specific error codes intended
      for programmatic evaluation and we use these error codes if the server
      provides them. However for PostgreSQL versions before 7.4, we require
      that the database server error language be in English (the
      '<code>C</code>' locale) so that we can parse the text error messages.
      If you are not running PostgreSQL 7.4 or newer, the installer executes a
      bogus query against the database and checks for an expected result in
      English.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="not-null-constraint-error">
      <title>Error: "Column X in new table has NOT NULL constraint
      ..."</title>

      <para>This is a warning that the installer might not update tables
      successfully. Make sure that your database is backed up, and run the
      installer again with the "-N" option to ignore this check.</para>

      <para>As an attempt to ensure that the install will complete
      successfully, a check is done to see if there might be any rows with
      NULL columns that might be inserted into a column in an upgrade table
      with a NOT NULL constraint. This usually happens when a previous run of
      the installer failed, or might be due to modifications to the database
      schema or a really old version of the schema.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="backup-tables-still-exists">
      <title>Error: "One or more backup tables from a previous install still
      exists"</title>

      <para>When the installer runs to upgrade the OpenNMS database from a
      previous install, it often updates table schemas. When it does this, it
      copies the data in a table to a temporary table (e.g.: the contents of
      <filename>node</filename> are copied into
      <filename>node_old_11033991291234</filename>). The original table is
      deleted, the new version of the table is created, the data in the
      temporary table is translated into the new table, and finally the
      temporary table is deleted.</para>

      <para>Unfortunately, the installer cannot check for all problems that
      might break translation, so sometimes the translation step fails. In
      this case, the installer "reverts" the table it was processing by
      dropping the new table and moving the temporary table into its
      place.</para>

      <para>Reverting the table in case of a problem is all good and well, but
      sometimes even it does not work properly, especially with older versions
      of the Java installer. If this happens, the temporary table (the one
      with "_old_" in it) is left with all of the old data. Until OpenNMS
      1.1.5, this problem would not be caught the next time you ran the
      installer. The installer would see that you did not have the
      <filename>node</filename> table, for example, and happily continue to
      create a new one for you. This is bad, especially since you probably
      still have data that you care about that is now in the "old"
      table.</para>

      <para>If you get this error, you will want to get rid of the table(s)
      containing "_old_", however you want to first check if they contain
      data. For example, if you have a single table,
      <filename>node_old_11033991291234</filename>, no other
      <filename>node_old_*</filename> tables, and no <filename>node</filename>
      table, you can simply rename the table:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>psql -h localhost -U opennms opennms</command>
<computeroutput>Welcome to psql 7.4.6, the PostgreSQL interactive terminal.

Type:  \copyright for distribution terms
       \h for help with SQL commands
       \? for help on internal slash commands
       \g or terminate with semicolon to execute query
       \q to quit

opennms=# </computeroutput><command>ALTER TABLE node_old_11033991291234 RENAME TO node;</command></programlisting>

      <para>You can use the "\d" command within <filename>psql</filename> to
      see what other tables exist in your database. You can use "<code>SELECT
      count(*) from table;</code>" (fill in the table name for "table") to get
      a count of rows in any table. If you have empty tables, you can just
      drop them. If you have multiple tables with data, you will have to
      decide which table of data you want to keep or merge them. This is left
      as a (not so simple) exercise for the reader.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="table-violates-new-constraint">
      <title>Error: "Table X contains N rows (out of M) that violate new
      constraint Y"</title>

      <para>Over time OpenNMS extends its database schema to improve
      functionality. This error can happen because of the way certain
      administrative functions in older versions of OpenNMS functioned or if
      the database was modified outside of OpenNMS (the latter is common for
      larger sites). Over time OpenNMS has introduced additional foreign key
      constraints on its database. These are used to ensure internal database
      consistency when data in two tables are tied together by a shared key.
      For example, each event can have a pointer to the node that it is
      related to; there is a foreign key constraint that requires that an
      event <emphasis>must not</emphasis> point at a node that does not
      exist.</para>

      <para>Starting with 1.1.5, when we upgrade the database schema, we first
      check for rows that violate any new foreign key constraints that might
      be added. There are three options to to fix these errors:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Remove the offending rows. This is suggested if the number of
          rows that violate the constraint is small in comparison to the total
          number of rows in the affected table and if you don't need the data.
          Use "<code>$OPENNMS_HOME/bin/install -C &lt;constraint&gt;
          -X</code>" to delete the offending rows.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Mark the key in the offending rows to NULL. This is suggested
          if you need to keep the data around or are not yet sure about what
          to do with it. Use "<code>$OPENNMS_HOME/bin/install -C
          &lt;constraint&gt;</code>" to mark the key column to NULL in the
          offending rows.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fix the key in the offending rows. This is for advanced users
          and requires a good amount of effort. This is left as an exercise
          for the reader.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="iplike-permission-denied">
      <title>Error: "- adding iplike database function... &lt;snip&gt;
      org.postgresql.util.PSQLException: ERROR: could not access file
      '&lt;snip&gt;/lib/iplike.so': Permission denied"</title>

      <para>The PostgreSQL server cannot access the iplike.so file. This could
      be due to the file itself not having appropriate permissions for the
      user that PostgreSQL runs as and/or one or more of the parent
      directories of the iplike.so not having appropriate permissions.</para>

      <para>This error is seen even when running the installer as root because
      it is not OpenNMS nor the installer that cannot access the iplike.so
      file, but the PostgreSQL database. The installer instructs the
      PostgreSQL database to load the iplike.so and the PostgreSQL database
      server usually runs as a non-root user, so it is subject to filesystem
      access control checks like any other normal user. This is commonly seen
      when people install OpenNMS into a home directory for root or another
      user and the permissions on that home directory do not allow users other
      than the owner of the directory access.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="iplike-coult-not-load-library">
      <title>Error: "- adding iplike database function... &lt;snip&gt;
      org.postgresql.util.PSQLException: ERROR: could not load library
      ..."</title>

      <para>The latter part of the error could be something like
      "<code>&lt;path&gt;/iplike.so: cannot open shared object file: No such
      file or directory</code>" or "<code>ld.so.1: postgres: fatal:
      &lt;path&gt;/iplike.so: wrong ELF class: ELFCLASS32</code>".</para>

      <para>The PostgreSQL server cannot load the <code>iplike.so</code> file.
      This is almost always caused by the PostgreSQL server and the iplike.so
      file being compiled for different processor instruction sets. This is
      commonly seen when the PostgreSQL server is compiled to use a 64-bit
      instruction set but the OpenNMS <code>iplike.so</code> shared object is
      compiled for a 32-bit instruction set, although the opposite is
      possible, as well. You can use the "<code>file</code>" command on
      <code>iplike.so</code> and the <code>postmaster</code> binary with
      PostgreSQL to check their instruction sets.</para>

      <para>The easiest solution is to see if there is a packaged version of
      OpenNMS compiled for the same instruction set (32- or 64-bit) as your
      PostgreSQL server. The next easiest method for most users is to switch
      the PostgreSQL server to match the instruction set that the
      <code>iplike.so</code> file was compiled for. For advanced users, you
      can compile OpenNMS yourself to fit the processor set that you need. See
      <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/message.php?msg_id=9531580">this
      post to the discuss list</ulink> for some pointers.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="relation-pg_user-does-not-exist">
      <title>Error: "Exception in thread "main"
      org.postgresql.util.PSQLException: ERROR: relation "pg_user" does not
      exist" when running installer.</title>

      <para>This error means the database was not created properly. Since the
      installer script is supposed to create the database, one might assume it
      is a problem with OpenNMS, but instead it is an issue with the SELinux
      portions of Red Hat 4 (and CentOS 4). Basically, the postgres init_db
      command is not able to write to /dev/null, and it fails without a useful
      error message.</para>

      <para>To get around this, run the following commands:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>stop postgres</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>rm -rf /var/lib/pgsql/data</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>/usr/sbin/setenforce 0</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>start postgres</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Note that step 2 will delete any changes you made to the
      postgresql configuration files and you'll need to redo them.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="filenotfound-exception-permission-denied">
      <title>Error: java.io.FileNotFoundException: ... (Permission
      denied)</title>

      <para>An exact example of this error is:
      "<code>java.io.FileNotFoundException: /opt/opennms/etc/users.xml
      (Permission denied)</code>".</para>

      <para>If the above error happens when using admin functions through
      the web interface, such as managing users, notifications, and adding
      nodes, then the Tomcat web server is running as a non-root user but
      you haven't changed the permissions on the configuration files so
      the Tomcat user can access them.  Go back and follow the instructions
      earlier in the install guide on setting up Tomcat to run as a non-root
      user.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="where-to-get-help">
    <title>Where to Get Help</title>

    <para>OpenNMS is a community supported project. Please keep that in mind
    when seeking help on the program, as no one gets paid to work on the
    project (unless it is through a commercial support contract).</para>

    <section id="release-notes">
      <title>The Release Notes</title>

      <para>Check the release notes for this release.  They are in the <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/docman/?group_id=4141">Documentation</ulink>
      section of the OpenNMS project page at SourceForge.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="opennms-web-site">
      <title>The OpenNMS Web Site</title>

      <para>The main OpenNMS <ulink url="http://www.opennms.org">site</ulink>
      is a Wiki. As a community project, there is a lot of good advice and
      information available there. In particular, we suggest checking the
      above-mentioned release notes, the <ulink
      url="http://www.opennms.org/index.php/FAQ">FAQ entries on the wiki</ulink>,
      the <ulink url="http://bugzilla.opennms.org/">bug database</ulink> and,
      of course, <ulink url="http://www.google.com/">Google</ulink>,
      before posting to a mailing list.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="mailing-lists">
      <title>The OpenNMS Mailing Lists</title>

      <para>OpenNMS maintains a number of active mailing lists <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=4141">on SourceForge</ulink>:</para>

      <glosslist>
        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/opennms-announce">opennms-announce</ulink></glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>A low traffic, moderated mailing list for OpenNMS
            announcements.  All posts to this list are duplicated on the
            <glossterm>opennms-discuss</glossterm> list.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/opennms-cvs">opennms-cvs</ulink></glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>This is a fairly high traffic list of all updates to the Subversion
            repositories on SourceForge.  Moderated.  Only SVN updates are posted here
            (no discussion).</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/opennms-devel">opennms-devel</ulink></glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>This list is for discussion of development of the OpenNMS codebase.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/opennms-discuss">opennms-discuss</ulink></glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>This is the main OpenNMS discuss list. It's pretty friendly, and
            reasonably high-volume.  It tends to focus on configuration issues and
            general discussion of network management, but pretty much anything goes
            here.  However, it is suggested that installation-related issues go to
            the <glossterm>opennms-install</glossterm> list instead.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/opennms-install">opennms-install</ulink></glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>This is a great list for new users to OpenNMS.  The main
            focus is installation issues (cleared up by this great documentation,
            right?) but most "newbie" questions are welcome here.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/opennms-maps">opennms-maps</ulink></glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>OpenNMS has a network map feature, which includes code for
            automatically determining relationships between hosts (Linkd).  This
            is the appropriate list for discussion of maps and the underlying
            Linkd code.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/opennms-windows">opennms-windows</ulink></glossterm>
          
          <glossdef>
            <para>A discussion list for people running OpenNMS on Windows.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        
        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/opennms-francais">opennms-francais</ulink></glossterm>
          
          <glossdef>
            <para>A list for discussion of OpenNMS in French.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        
        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/opennms-italia">opennms-italia</ulink></glossterm>
          
          <glossdef>
            <para>A list for discussion of OpenNMS in Italian.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        
        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/opennms-ug-tokyo">opennms-ug-tokyo</ulink></glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>A list for discussion of OpenNMS in Japanese, as well as
            general discussion among the Tokyo OpenNMS Users Group.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        
        <glossentry>
          <glossterm><ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/opennms-ug-uk">opennms-ug-uk</ulink></glossterm>
          
          <glossdef>
            <para>A list for discussion of OpenNMS in UK English for those 
            who don't speak American English (OK, just kidding).  Actually,
            a discussion list for the UK OpenNMS Users Group.  ;)</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
        
      </glosslist>

      <para>The OpenNMS mailing lists are also archived at <ulink
      url="http://search.gmane.org">gmane.org</ulink>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="commercial-support">
      <title>Commercial Support</title>

      <para>If you are using OpenNMS in a production environment, or are
      considering it, you might be interested in commercial support. The
      <ulink url="http://www.opennms.com/">OpenNMS Group</ulink>
      maintains the OpenNMS project, and we also offer support, training,
      consulting services and custom development.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
