<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Troubleshooting an OpenNMS Installation</title>

  <section>
    <title>Common Installation Issues</title>

    <para>The following section contains advice for overcoming common
    installation issues.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Dependency Problems</title>

      <para>To assist with code management, the easiest way to install OpenNMS
      is via packages. Every effort has been made to insure that the packages
      OpenNMS depends on are required before the OpenNMS package can be
      installed. You should be able to find those packages on the distribution
      CDs that came with your system. For some of the more obscure packages,
      like <filename>metamail</filename>, you can visit the OpenNMS <ulink
      url="ftp://ftp.opennms.org">FTP</ulink> site and check in the
      <filename>/pub/dependencies</filename> directory. In addition, sites
      like <ulink url="http://distro.ibiblio.org/">Ibiblio</ulink> and <ulink
      url="http://www.freshrpms.net">FreshRPMs</ulink> are also good
      sources.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The OpenNMS Application Won't Start</title>

      <para>If the OpenNMS is installed, and the packages were not forced in
      using options like "<code>--nodeps</code>", the application should run
      just fine. If not, OpenNMS has a robust logging facility. Change to the
      logs directory (usually <filename>/var/log/opennms</filename>) and
      search the logs, using <filename>grep</filename> or your tool of choice,
      for words like <code>FATAL</code> and <code>ERROR</code> (the two
      highest log severities). Those events should give you clues as to why
      OpenNMS is not working.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>DHCP Poller Won't Start</title>

      <para>The OpenNMS DHCP poller will fail to start most operating systems
      (Linux, in particular) if you are running a DHCP client on the OpenNMS
      server. You'll see this by running "<code>opennms -v status</code>" and
      seeing everything in the <code>RUNNING</code> state, except for
      <code>Dhcpd</code>. The solution is to edit
      <filename>$OPENNMS_HOME/etc/service-configuration.xml</filename> and
      comment-out the "<code>&lt;service&gt;...&lt;/service&gt;</code>" stanza
      for <code>Dhcpd</code>. For example, this is what the section would look
      like after modification to disable <code>Dhcpd</code>:</para>

      <programlisting>        &lt;!-- Commented out since we have a DHCP client on this server
        &lt;service&gt;
                &lt;name&gt;OpenNMS:Name=Dhcpd&lt;/name&gt;
                &lt;class-name&gt;org.opennms.netmgt.dhcpd.jmx.Dhcpd&lt;/class-name&gt;
                &lt;invoke pass="1" method="start"/&gt;
                &lt;invoke at="status" pass="0" method="status"/&gt;
                &lt;invoke at="stop" pass="0" method="stop"/&gt;
        &lt;/service&gt;
        --&gt;</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The OpenNMS Web Application Will Not Start, or You Can't Log
      In</title>

      <para>There are actually two main applications in the OpenNMS product:
      the application itself and the web-based User Interface (webUI). The
      webUI is implemented via Tomcat, and it is possible for Tomcat to be
      running and the OpenNMS application to be stopped and vice versa.</para>

      <para>Before you do anything else, check the platform-specific
      installation notes in this guide. There are a number of common problems
      with Tomcat which are covered there.</para>

      <para>If you can't get to the OpenNMS interface
      (<filename>http://[opennms server]:8080/opennms</filename> or
      <filename>http://[opennms server]:8180/opennms</filename> on Debian -
      where [opennms server] is the name of the OpenNMS machine) make sure
      that Tomcat is running, and if necessary restart it. You should also be
      able to access the main Tomcat page by leaving off the
      "<filename>/opennms</filename>".</para>

      <para>Check to make sure that the OpenNMS web application is installed
      correctly. In Tomcat's <varname>CATALINA_HOME</varname> (usually
      <filename>/var/tomcat4</filename>), you should see a sub-directory
      called <filename>webapps</filename>. Starting in OpenNMS 1.1.4, we no
      longer place the OpenNMS webapp directly into this
      <filename>webapps</filename> directory. Inside of
      <filename>webapps</filename>, you should only see a file (or symbolic
      link) called <filename>opennms.xml</filename>. If you see a directory
      (or symbolic link) called <filename>opennms</filename>, delete it (this
      is not done automatically by the installer when upgrading).</para>

      <para>Also in <varname>CATALINA_HOME</varname> there is a sub-directory
      called conf and in that directory is a file called
      <filename>server.xml</filename>. Before OpenNMS 1.1.4, we needed to add
      a "context" to that file, however this is no longer needed in OpenNMS
      1.1.4. In fact, if you are upgrading from 1.1.3 or earlier, you must
      manually remove this "context" from <filename>server.xml</filename> (it
      is not done automatically when upgrading). Here is what it looks like
      looks like:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;!-- Example Server Configuration File --&gt;
&lt;Server ...
...
  ...
    &lt;Host ... &gt;
      ....
      &lt;Context path="/opennms" docBase="opennms" debug="0" reloadable="true"&gt;
        &lt;Logger classname="org.opennms.web.log.Log4JLogger" homeDir="/opt/OpenNMS"/&gt;
        &lt;Realm className="org.opennms.web.authenticate.OpenNMSTomcatRealm" homeDir="/opt/OpenNMS"/&gt;
      &lt;/Context &gt;
    &lt;/Host &gt;
  ...
&lt;/Server &gt;</programlisting>

      <para>Tomcat will also need to be aware of various OpenNMS JARs and
      libraries which provide the Java classes which make these directives
      work. To give tomcat access to these resources, links are created in
      <filename>$CATALINA_HOME/server/lib</filename> pointing to the locations
      of the following OpenNMS JARs:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>castor-0.9.3.9.jar -&gt;
          /opt/OpenNMS/lib/castor-0.9.3.9.jar</filename></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>log4j.jar -&gt;
          /opt/OpenNMS/lib/log4j.jar</filename></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>opennms_common.jar -&gt;
          /opt/OpenNMS/lib/opennms_common.jar</filename></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>opennms_core.jar -&gt;
          /opt/OpenNMS/lib/opennms_core.jar</filename></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename><filename>opennms_services.jar -&gt;
          /opt/OpenNMS/lib/opennms_services.jar</filename></filename></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>opennms_web.jar -&gt;
          /opt/OpenNMS/lib/opennms_web.jar</filename></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Tomcat has a "working" directory (usually
      <filename>$CATALINA_HOME/work</filename>) where it stores the Java
      source for JSP pages as well as the compiled classes for JSPs. Sometimes
      users see problems with the webapp until the working directory is
      cleared and Tomcat is restarted. We suggest running "<code>rm -rf
      <filename>$CATALINA_HOME/work</filename></code>" if the above items fail
      to get the webapp working.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>"runjava: Could not find an appropriate JRE"</title>

      <para>The <code><filename>runjava</filename></code> program is used to
      locate a suitable JRE for OpenNMS at install time that will be used for
      the installer and also for running OpenNMS after installation. See the
      section earlier in this manual on installing Java for OpenNMS. If you
      insatalled Java in a location that <code>runjava</code> cannot find, you
      can use its "<code>-f</code>" option to specify the JRE you want OpenNMS
      to use.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>"The database server's error messages are not in English
      ..."</title>

      <para>You either need to set "<code>lc_messages = 'C'</code>" in your
      postgresql.conf file and restart PostgreSQL or upgrade to PostgreSQL 7.4
      or later.</para>

      <para>The installer does not always verify that an operation will
      succeed before executing the operation (e.g.: dropping database
      functions). In this case, it catches the exceptions returned from the
      database and checks the exception to see if it is an "okay" exception
      that should be ignored (e.g.: if the database function does not exist
      when attempting to drop a function).</para>

      <para>In PostgreSQL 7.4 and later, a new client/server protocol is used
      (version 3, to be specific) that provides specific error codes intended
      for programmatic evaluation and we use these error codes if the server
      provides them. However for PostgreSQL versions before 7.4, we require
      that the database server error language be in English (the
      '<code>C</code>' locale) so that we can parse the text error messages.
      If you are not running PostgreSQL 7.4 or newer, the installer executes a
      bogus query against the database and checks for an expected result in
      English.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>"Column X in new table has NOT NULL constraint ..."</title>

      <para>This is a warning that the installer might not update tables
      successfully. Make sure that your database is backed up, and run the
      installer again with the "-N" option to ignore this check.</para>

      <para>As an attempt to ensure that the install will complete
      successfully, a check is done to see if there might be any rows with
      NULL columns that might be inserted into a column in an upgrade table
      with a NOT NULL constraint. This usually happens when a previous run of
      the installer failed, or might be due to modifications to the database
      schema or a really old version of the schema.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>"One or more backup tables from a previous install still
      exists"</title>

      <para>When the installer runs to upgrade the OpenNMS database from a
      previous install, it often updates table schemas. When it does this, it
      copies the data in a table to a temporary table (e.g.: the contents of
      <filename>node</filename> are copied into
      <filename>node_old_11033991291234</filename>). The original table is
      deleted, the new version of the table is created, the data in the
      temporary table is translated into the new table, and finally the
      temporary table is deleted.</para>

      <para>Unfortunately, the installer cannot check for all problems that
      might break translation, so sometimes the translation step fails. In
      this case, the installer "reverts" the table it was processing by
      dropping the new table and moving the temporary table into its
      place.</para>

      <para>Reverting the table in case of a problem is all good and well, but
      sometimes even it does not work properly, especially with older versions
      of the Java installer. If this happens, the temporary table (the one
      with "_old_" in it) is left with all of the old data. Until OpenNMS
      1.1.5, this problem would not be caught the next time you ran the
      installer. The installer would see that you did not have the
      <filename>node</filename> table, for example, and happily continue to
      create a new one for you. This is bad, especially since you probably
      still have data that you care about that is now in the "old"
      table.</para>

      <para>If you get this error, you will want to get rid of the table(s)
      containing "_old_", however you want to first check if they contain
      data. For example, if you have a single table,
      <filename>node_old_11033991291234</filename>, no other
      <filename>node_old_*</filename> tables, and no <filename>node</filename>
      table, you can simply rename the table:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>psql -h localhost -U opennms opennms</command>
<computeroutput>Welcome to psql 7.4.6, the PostgreSQL interactive terminal.

Type:  \copyright for distribution terms
       \h for help with SQL commands
       \? for help on internal slash commands
       \g or terminate with semicolon to execute query
       \q to quit

opennms=# </computeroutput><command>ALTER TABLE node_old_11033991291234 RENAME TO node;</command></programlisting>

      <para>You can use the "\d" command within <filename>psql</filename> to
      see what other tables exist in your database. You can use
      "<filename>SELECT count(*) from table</filename>;" (fill in the table
      name for "table") to get a count of rows in any table. If you have empty
      tables, you can just drop them. If you have multiple tables with data,
      you will have to decide which table of data you want to keep or merge
      them. This is left as a (not so simple) exercise for the reader.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Where to Get Help</title>

    <para>OpenNMS is a community supported project. Please keep that in mind
    when seeking help on the program, as no one gets paid to work on the
    project (unless it is through a commercial support contract).</para>

    <section>
      <title>The OpenNMS Web Site</title>

      <para>The main OpenNMS <ulink url="http://www.opennms.org">site</ulink>
      is a Wiki. As a community project, there is a lot of good advice and
      information available there. In particular, we suggest checking the
      <ulink url="http://wiki.opennms.org/tiki-list_faqs.php">FAQ</ulink> and
      the <ulink
      url="http://bugzilla.opennms.org/cgi-bin/bugzilla/index.cgi">bug
      database</ulink>. You might also find useful information in the <ulink
      url="http://faq.opennms.org/">old FAQ</ulink>, but please realize that
      this information may be out of date.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The OpenNMS Mailing Lists</title>

      <para>OpenNMS maintains a number of active mailing lists on
      SourceForge:</para>

      <glosslist>
        <glossentry>
          <glossterm>opennms-announce</glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>A low traffic, moderated mailing list for OpenNMS
            announcements. All posts to this list are duplicated on the
            <glossterm>opennms-discuss</glossterm> list.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm>opennms-cvs</glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>This is a fairly high traffic list of all updates to the CVS
            repositories on SourceForge. Moderated. Only CVS updates are
            posted here (no discussion).</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm>opennms-devel</glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>This list is for code development discussion.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm>opennms-discuss</glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>This is the main OpenNMS discuss list. Its pretty friendly.
            Pretty much anything goes here, however it is suggested that
            installation-related issues to go
            <glossterm>opennms-install</glossterm>.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm>opennms-install</glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>This is a great list for new users to OpenNMS. The main
            focus is installation issues (cleared up by this great
            documentation, right?) but most "newbie" questions are welcome
            here.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm>opennms-maps</glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>Whether or not to use maps in network management is as
            divisive an issue as abortion or gun control (grin). OpenNMS does
            have a small contributed map system, which still needs a lot of
            work. We can talk about it here.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>

        <glossentry>
          <glossterm>opennms-ug-tokyo</glossterm>

          <glossdef>
            <para>We have a small users group in Tokyo, Japan. This list is
            for meeting announcements or help in Japanese.</para>
          </glossdef>
        </glossentry>
      </glosslist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Commercial Support</title>

      <para>If you are using OpenNMS in a production environment, or are
      considering it, you might be interested in commercial support. The
      <ulink url="http://www.opennms.com/opennms_about.html">OpenNMS
      Group</ulink> maintains the OpenNMS project, and we also offer support,
      training, consulting services and custom development.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
