<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="chap4">
  <title>Supported Systems</title>

  <subtitle>Supported UNIX-like OSes</subtitle>

  <para>OpenNMS is written almost entirely in Java, and should be able to run
  on any system that supports the Sun Java Virtual Machine (Java 1.4 for
  OpenNMS 1.2.x, Java 5 or 6 for OpenNMS 1.3.x). There are requirements for
  other programs such as PostgreSQL, Perl, and (for OpenNMS 1.2.x) Tomcat 4
  and RRDTool, but the JDK is the key requirement as most of the other
  packages can be compiled from source.</para>

  <para>The following are the systems that support or are known to run
  OpenNMS.</para>

  <para>Windows 2000/XP/Vista are to be supported with 1.3.8.</para>

  <section id="chap4sect1">
    <title>Fully Supported</title>

    <para>The following Linux distributions and other Unix-like systems are
    supported out-of-the-box with native installation packages.</para>

    <bridgehead>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 3, Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4 and Red
    Hat Enterprise Linux 5</bridgehead>

    <bridgehead>CentOS 3, CentOS 4 and CentOS 5</bridgehead>

    <bridgehead>Fedora Core 4, Fedora Core 5, Fedora Core 6, Fedora Core 7 and
    Fedora Core 8 (including 64 bit).</bridgehead>

    <bridgehead>Solaris 10 on x86 and SPARC</bridgehead>

    <bridgehead>SuSE 9 and SuSE 10</bridgehead>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Debian and Ubuntu</title>

      <para>Debian stable (1.2.x) packages (for Sarge and later) are available
      at the following apt-repository: <programlisting>deb http://debian.opennms.org/ stable main</programlisting>.
      Debian unstable (1.3.x) packages (for Etch and later) are available at
      the following apt-repository: <programlisting>deb http://debian.opennms.org/ unstable main</programlisting>.
      For more instructions see this <ulink
      url="http://opennms.netstatz.com/Debian_ONMS_HOWTO.html#toc2">How-To</ulink>
      written by Ian MacDonald.</para>

      <para>These same packages and apt-repositories should work equally well
      with recent Ubuntu releases. The unstable (1.3.x) packages in particular
      are tested to work with Ubuntu releases 6.10 (Edgy Eft) and 7.04 (Feisty
      Fawn). The lack of a <programlisting>sun-java5-jdk</programlisting>
      package in any official repository for LTS release 6.06 (Dapper Drake)
      disqualifies this release as a viable target for official OpenNMS
      packages.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title>MacOSX 10.4 (Tiger), 10.5 (Leopard)</title>

      <para>On MacOSX, the Fink distribution packages of OpenNMS are
      supported. See <ulink url="http://www.finkproject.org/">the Fink web
      site</ulink> for more information on installing and using Fink.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <para>Also note that on MacOSX, PostgreSQL must be configured in the same
    manner as above for Linux. <emphasis>However</emphasis>, to do so you will
    need to update the SHM settings so that the OS allows enough resources for
    PostgreSQL to run with larger buffers.</para>

    <para>There are details for configuring the shared memory segments on
    <ulink
    url="http://wiki.finkproject.org/index.php/Shared_Memory_Regions_on_Darwin">the
    Fink wiki</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="chap4sect2">
    <title>Officially Unsupported</title>

    <para>OpenNMS 1.3.7 requires Java 5 (a 1.5 JDK), RRDTool 1.2 (for optional
    features), and PostgreSQL 7.4, 8.1, or 8.2. Any operating system that can
    support these dependencies should be able to run OpenNMS. However, since
    many older distributions do not support packages for these applications it
    will be much harder to get them installed, and so they are not officially
    supported.</para>

    <para>A number of distributions that used to be supported are still able
    to run OpenNMS but are not officially supported:</para>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Mandrake</title>

      <para>OpenNMS should run on Mandrake, and official Mandriva support is
      expected for OpenNMS 2.0.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Gentoo</title>

      <para>Information on Gentoo support can be found at <ulink
      url="http://gentoo.opennms.org">http://gentoo.opennms.org</ulink>.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <bridgehead>Red Hat 7, Red Hat 8 and Red Hat 9</bridgehead>

    <bridgehead>SuSE 8</bridgehead>

    <bridgehead>Solaris 8 and Solaris 9</bridgehead>
  </section>
</chapter>