<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="supported">
  <title>Supported Systems</title>

  <subtitle>Supported UNIX-like OSes</subtitle>

  <para>OpenNMS is written almost entirely in Java, and should be able to run
  on any system that supports the Sun Java Virtual Machine -- OpenNMS 1.3.x and
  higher requires Java 5 or higher.  There are requirements for
  other programs such as PostgreSQL and Perl, but the JDK is the key requirement
  as most of the other packages can be compiled from source.</para>

  <para>The following are the systems that support or are known to run
  OpenNMS.</para>

  <para>Windows 2000/XP/Vista are supported as of 1.3.8.</para>

  <section id="supported-fully">
    <title>Fully Supported</title>

    <para>The following systems are supported out-of-the-box with native installation packages:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
				<title>RPM-based Distributions (Using Yum)</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>Red hat Enterprise Linux 3 and higher</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>CentOS 3 and higher</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>Fedora Core 4 and higher (including 64-bit)</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>SuSE Linux 9 and 10 (Using the Yum repository through YAST)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
				<title>Other RPM-based Distributions</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>Mandriva Linux 2007 and higher (Using URPMI)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
				<title>Debian and Ubuntu Linux</title>
				<para>Debian packages for Etch and later are available at the following
				apt repository:</para>
				<programlisting>deb http://debian.opennms.org/ unstable main</programlisting>
				<para>These same packages should work equally well with Ubuntu releases
				6.10 (Edgy Eft) and higher.</para>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem><para>Solaris 10 (X86 and SPARC)</para></listitem>
		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
				<title>MacOSX 10.4 and Higher</title>
				<para>On MacOSX, the Fink distribution <ulink
				url="http://pdb.finkproject.org/pdb/package.php/opennms">packages of OpenNMS</ulink>
				are supported. See <ulink url="http://www.finkproject.org/">the Fink web
				site</ulink> for more information on installing and using Fink.</para>

				<para>Also note that on MacOSX, PostgreSQL must be configured in the same
				manner as above for Linux. <emphasis>However</emphasis>, to do so you will
				need to update the SHM settings so that the OS allows enough resources for
				PostgreSQL to run with larger buffers.</para>

				<para>There are details for configuring the shared memory segments on <ulink
				url="http://wiki.finkproject.org/index.php/Shared_Memory_Regions_on_Darwin">the
				Fink wiki</ulink>.</para>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
				<title>Windows Server and Desktop (Windows 2000+)</title>

				<para>
					Note that while it is technically possible to install on FAT32, NTFS
					is the only officially supported filesystem for Windows installs.
					Additionally, while Windows is supported, OpenNMS is much more heavily
					tested (and easier to maintain) on UNIX, and it is recommended that
					unless you have a specific reason to go with Windows, that you use
					one of the supported UNIX-based operating systems.
				</para>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="supported-unsupported">
    <title>Unsupported</title>

    <para>OpenNMS 1.3.7 and up require Java 5 (a 1.5 JDK) and PostgreSQL 7.4 or higher.
    In addition, for native RRD support (as opposed to the builtin Java-based JRobin
    round-robin database), RRDTool 1.2 is required.</para>

    <para>Any operating system that can
    support these dependencies should be able to run OpenNMS. However, since
    many older distributions do not support packages for these applications it
    will be much harder to get them installed, and so they are not officially
    supported.</para>

    <para>A number of distributions that used to be supported are still able
    to run OpenNMS but are not officially supported:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
				<title>Gentoo</title>

				<para>Gentoo ebuilds are available but are not officially supported,
				as we depend on Gentoo packager volunteers from the at-large user
				community to keep them up-to-date. Information is available
				<ulink
				url="http://www.opennms.org/wiki/Other_Install_instructions#Gentoo_Installation">
				on the wiki</ulink>.
				</para>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<formalpara>
				<title>Red Hat Linux</title>
				<para>While Red hat Linux 7, 8, and 9 (and potentially even others
				might still work, they have long gone untested and are not recommended
				for production use.</para>
			</formalpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem><para>SuSE 8 and earlier</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Solaris 9 and earlier</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

  </section>
</chapter>
