<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="chap1">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <subtitle>About This Release</subtitle>

  <para>Release 1.5.90 is the first in a series of betas and release
  candidates for OpenNMS 1.6.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.5.90 is "tubeweasel"</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.11 fixes a bug with events in 1.3.10.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.3.11 is "oopsy"</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.10 is another bug fix/feature release. It contains a lot
  of bug fixes in preparation for the next stable release 1.6.0, as well as
  some changes to thresholding. In addition, OpenNMS now supports integration
  with the Hyperic HQ agent.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.3.10 is "caucus"</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.9 is a small bug fix/feature release. A bug was fixed that
  could cause database connections to hang, and some small webUI enhancements
  were made.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.3.9 is "thanksgiving"</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.8 is the next step on the road toward 1.8. Lots of bug
  fixes and some new features. The biggest news is initial support for running
  OpenNMS on Windows.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.3.8 is "redmond"</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.7 is probably the best OpenNMS ever released. It removes
  the need for Tomcat, adds several new features including a SmokePing clone
  called StrafePing, and includes several performance enhancements.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.3.7 is "speedy"</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.6 is the first release where the main OpenNMS application
  is pure Java. All of the C-based JNI code has been moved to packages outside
  of OpenNMS proper.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.3.6 is "blink"</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.5 is a replacement for the aborted 1.3.4 release. It
  really fixes the notifications issue. In addition, some performance
  enhancements have been made to how data collection is started.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.3.5 is "expelliarmus"</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.4 is a bugfix release against 1.3.3. Hey, release early
  and often. It fixes an issue with notifications triggered by trap events not
  working.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.3.4 is "ooops"</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.3 is yet another major step toward OpenNMS 2.0. It should
  be considered much more stable than 1.3.2, so please disregard most of the
  scary warnings below, but if something should break we reserve the right to
  point one of them out. This release adds a new read-only Dashboard view
  using Google Web Toolkit, a new API for integrating with trouble ticketing
  systems (currently supporting Centric CRM), correlation rules and a number
  of other features. It also marks the start of our repackaging effort to move
  all C code out of the main OpenNMS branch, starting with the iplike
  postgresql function.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.3.3 is "e-peen"</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.2 is a seriously huge upgrade to the OpenNMS application.
  It should be considered the pre-Alpha version of OpenNMS 2.0. It will most
  likely break your network, destroy your sanity, and cause you to put on
  sackcloth and wander the world as a beggar. That said, several people are
  using it in production, but please, do so at your own risk. Expect a hard
  upgrade path from OpenNMS 1.2, although fresh installs should be pretty
  simple. There are lots of really cool things in 1.3.2, so it is as least
  worth checking out on a development box. Please, don't use it in production
  unless you are experienced with OpenNMS and understand the risks.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.3.2 is "happynewyear"</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.1 is a bug fix release to address an issue with a database
  connection leak. It also includes more NRPE client code and a new "examples"
  directory.</para>

  <para>Release 1.3.0 is the first "development" release on the road to
  version 1.4.0. As a development release, it should be considered unstable
  for use in production environments, but you are encouraged to try it out. It
  contains a number of features such as a new alarms subsystem, automations
  via vacuumd, SNMP version 3 support, JMX data collection and more. Please,
  please note the "in progress" nature of this release, as large amounts of
  code have been rewritten. Unless you have a commercial support agreement or
  are just very brave, don't use it in production.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.3.0 is "wererabbit"</para>

  <para>Release 1.2.5 is an important maintenance release for the stable
  branch of OpenNMS. It includes a major bug fix concerning possible polling
  deadlocks that can cause outages that are never resolved, as well as a large
  improvement to SNMP data collection speed and startup time.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.2.5 is "gromit".</para>

  <para>Release 1.2.4 is yet another maintenance release for OpenNMS. It
  includes a few minor bug fixes, some new configurations, and a couple of
  small features.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.2.4 is "wootness".</para>

  <para>Release 1.2.3 is another maintenance release in the OpenNMS stable
  branch. It addresses a polling issue that may cause polling to stop, as well
  as adding a final version of the poll-outages calendar. Also included are a
  number of new events and reports.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.2.3 is "sith".</para>

  <para>Release 1.2.2 is 1.2.1 with one annoying webUI bug fixed.</para>

  <para>Release 1.2.1 is a maintenance release in the OpenNMS stable branch.
  It contains a few bug fixes and several small features. "Stable" releases
  may contain new features, as long as it is determined that they pose a very
  small risk to current features. Usually, these features will add new
  functionality without modifying existing feature behavior.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.2.1 is "luckycharms".</para>

  <para>Release 1.2.0 is the first stable, or production, release of OpenNMS
  in a long time. It is basically 1.1.5 with numerous bug fixes. With the
  release of 1.2.0, we will begin development on 1.3 - the next unstable
  release.</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.2.0 is "valentine".</para>

  <para>Release 1.1.5 is the second release candidate for 1.2. The biggest
  change involves poller code that has been nearly rewritten. This was in
  response to a new feature concerning notifications, and while we believe it
  to be very robust, it does represent a lot of code churn, so if you are
  using 1.1.4 in production, you may wish to wait a bit before upgrading to
  1.1.5.</para>

  <para>Also, with this version of the release notes, we are implementing a
  "code word". We try to make these notes useful, including tips on the
  majority of issues people will face while using the application, but still
  people tend to skip reading them. So now, if you want to post a
  1.1.5-related question on the mailing lists, be sure to include the code
  word so people will know you have at least read this far into the release
  notes (grin).</para>

  <para>The code word for 1.1.5 is "monsoon".</para>

  <para>A quick summary of the new changes in 1.1.5, in no particular
  order:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>New notification behavior - users can configure OpenNMS to send
      notices when an event is auto-acknowledged by notifd and they will only
      be sent to those people who received notice of the outage in the first
      place.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A new RADIUS poller</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A number of new event definitions, including those from NetBotz,
      PATROL, Network Appliance and others.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Reorganized the <filename>datacollection-config.xml</filename> and
      <filename>snmp-graph.properties</filename> files to make them easier to
      manage. Also added a really cool CPU report for Net-SNMP agents.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>KSC Reports can now be accessed from the main page.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Removed the need for a primary SNMP interface (i.e. the ability to
      map an ifIndex to an IP Address in the ipAddrTable. This will help with
      data collection from some devices.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Added database support for the ifAlias field.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Added a MATCH-ANY-UEI event. Useful in notifications, this event
      will cause a notification on any UEI. Now, for example, all events from
      a particular IP Address or Node can be sent as notifications.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>There were also a large number of bug fixes and other small
  enhancements made to the code. Please test the heck out of this release and
  be sure to add issues to bugzilla (<ulink
  url="http://bugzilla.opennms.org">http://bugzilla.opennms.org</ulink>) and
  we'll get 1.2.0 out as soon as possible.</para>

  <para>Release 1.1.4 is the release candidate for 1.2 - the next stable
  branch of OpenNMS. It represents a tremendous amount of work in the areas of
  speed and performance. It incorporates many changes and bug fixes to make
  OpenNMS more Java centric - including a new installer. Current production
  users should note that this release contains a lot more changes to the
  underlying code than any release since 1.1.0, so if you are currently happy
  with 1.1.3 or an earlier version, you may want to wait a week or two before
  upgrading, or wait until 1.2.</para>

  <para>OpenNMS 1.1.3 is a major milestone on the way to the next stable
  release, 1.2. It contains a number of improvements, especially under the
  covers, and is the first release created under the new build system.</para>

  <para>OpenNMS 1.1.2 adds several new features and bug fixes. New features
  include a JDBC poller, a script-based poller and script-based event handler,
  as well as contributed support for a map.</para>

  <para>OpenNMS 1.1.1 is the next step towards the production 1.2 release. It
  contains a number of new features and bug fixes.</para>

  <para>OpenNMS 1.1 extends the work that was begun with 1.0 to make OpenNMS
  more powerful and easier to use. Almost all of the new functionality was
  suggested by current OpenNMS users. It is hoped that these improvements will
  prove useful, and will lead to even more suggestions on how to improve the
  product.</para>

  <para>OpenNMS 1.0.2 is a maintenance release that fixes several code
  issues.</para>

  <para>OpenNMS 1.0.1 is a maintenance release that fixes several code
  issues.</para>

  <para>Please, let us know if you have any problems at all at the <ulink
  url="http://bugzilla.opennms.org/">OpenNMS Bugzilla</ulink> page.</para>
</chapter>