<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="known-issues">
	<title>Known Issues and Caveats</title>

	<para>Here is the list of known issues in this release of OpenNMS.</para>


	<section id="current-release">
		<title>Current Release</title>
		<para>There are no known major issues in OpenNMS 1.6.3.</para>
		<para>
			There are, however, a number of bugs and features which are slated for
			future 1.6 releases.  They can be viewed (and voted on) in the bugzilla <ulink
			url="http://bugzilla.opennms.org/buglist.cgi?target_milestone=future+1.6">future 1.6
			milestone</ulink>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="previous-releases">
		<title>Previous Releases</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>OpenNMS 1.6.0</title>

					<para>A few small issues were found in the release candidates that did not make
					it into 1.6.0.  They will be a part of the 1.6.1 release.</para>

					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>KSC reports sort by ID rather than by name (Bug <ulink
						url="http://bugzilla.opennms.org/show_bug.cgi?id=2817">#2817</ulink>)</para></listitem>

						<listitem><para>Graphs for load averages should show typical units
						rather than si units (Bug <ulink
						url="http://bugzilla.opennms.org/show_bug.cgi?id=2824">#2824</ulink>)</para></listitem>

						<listitem><para>A URL added in the discovery admin UI cannot be
						deleted. (Bug <ulink
						url="http://bugzilla.opennms.org/show_bug.cgi?id=2829">#2829</ulink>)</para></listitem>

					</itemizedlist>
				</formalpara>
				<formalpara>
					<title>OpenNMS 1.5.93</title>
					<para>OpenNMS is still not 100% compatible with PostgreSQL 8.3, because of
					a change in behavior regarding implicit casts.  Until we can fix our code to
					not rely on implicit casts, a workaround is available
					<ulink url="http://people.planetpostgresql.org/peter/index.php?/archives/18-Readding-implicit-casts-in-PostgreSQL-8.3.html">here</ulink>,
					but it is recommended that you stick with PostgreSQL 7.4 to 8.2 for production
					environments until this issue is resolved.</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>OpenNMS 1.5.90 Known Issues</title>
					<para>Editing scheduled outages in the web UI has a number of bugs.</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>OpenNMS 1.3.10 Known Issues</title>
					<para>Events that reference an IP address that exists on more than one
					node will not be processed. Fixed in 1.3.11.</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>OpenNMS 1.3.9 Known Issues</title>
					<para>The User Account Self-Service window (i.e. the page that allows
					users to change their passwords) will cause a warning that the application
					is trying to close a window on IE6.</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>OpenNMS 1.3.8 Known Issues</title>

					<para>The order of elements in some of the XML configuration files is
					enforced more strictly than before. This change may cause problems with
					customized OpenNMS configuration files (especially event definitions) that
					worked fine with previous releases. Correcting the ordering of elements in
					these files against the XML schema definitions (available from the <ulink
					url="http://www.opennms.org/">wiki</ulink>) may be necessary.</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>OpenNMS 1.3.7 Known Issues</title>

					<para>The zoom feature will not work on Windows using IE or Opera. The
					 workaround is to use Firefox. (corrected in 1.3.8)</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>OpenNMS 1.3.5 Known Issues</title>

					<para>Notification on the "newSuspect" event will fail. Bug <ulink
					url="http://bugzilla.opennms.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1954">#1954</ulink></para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
  </section>

</chapter>
