<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="chap6" label="6">
	<title>Chapter 6</title>
	<subtitle>Reporting</subtitle>
	<para>
	Access the main reporting page by clicking "reporting" in the 
	main menu.  From this point there are 3 options, performance reports, 
	custom performance reports and availability reports.  In this section 
	we will look at each type of report, and how to generate and interpret 
	the graphs and information provided.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="chap6sect1" label="6.1">
		<title>Performance Reports</title>
		<para>
		Clicking on "Performance Reports" will display a list of options 
		for generating the standard performance reports.
		</para>
		<para>
		In the leftmost select box, choose an interface to generate a report 
		on.  Select any one SNMP capable interface.  Next, 
		choose what information to report on.  Select 
		any number of options in the second column.  Select at least
		one option in each of the first 2 columns.  Lastly, choose 
		the timeframe to report on.
		</para>
		<para>
		After selecting the options, press the "Submit" button to be taken to 
		a bookmarkable page containing the resulting reports.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap6sect2" label="6.2">
		<title>Custom Performance Reports</title>
		<para>
		After selecting "Reports" from the main menu select "Custom Performance Report".  
		At this point, you will be guided through a series of questions about 
		the report you would like to create.  First choose the interface on which 
		you would like to report.  Next you need to select between 1 and 4 data 
		sources to report on.  For each data source you can choose a title, color, 
		line style and the type of value.  Finally choose a title for you graph as 
		well as a time period to report on.  From this point, selecting next should 
		display a bookmarkable graph.  The complete address of this graph can be 
		sent to another user via email, or instant message.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap6sect3" label="6.3">
		<title>Availability Reports</title>
		<para>
		After selecting "Reports" from the main menu select "Availability Report".  
		From this point simply select the type of report you would like to create, 
		and the category you would like to report on.  Pressing the "Get Report" button 
		will open the requested report in a new browser window.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
