<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="chap8" label="8">
	<title>Chapter 8</title>
	<subtitle>Assets</subtitle>
	<para>
	!!!Important!!!: Please read this entire section, before you enter any asset information.
	</para>
	<para>
	Asset information helps you keep track of information about your managed devices.  
	It can be used as search criteria, and is very handy in troubleshooting when 
	you need a phone number for a vendor, or wish to document peculiar behavior for 
	the next person that may access this information.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="chap8sect1" label="8.1">
		<title>Adding Asset information</title>
		<para>
		Use the search page to find the node you would like to add asset 
		information to, and click it.  Then click "Asset Info".  Fill out 
		whatever fields you think you need.  Click submit.  When entering 
		asset information, be very careful not to use any commas in any 
		fields if you plan to export or import your data.  THERE IS CURRENTLY 
		NO WAY TO ESCAPE COMMAS IN THE CURRENT VERSION.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="chap8sect2" label="8.2">
		<title>Search Nodes based on Asset Information</title>
		<para>
		Go to the search page or asset page and enter the criterium, and search.
		</para>
	</sect1>
        <sect1 id="chap8sect3" label="8.3">
                <title>Exporting Asset Information</title>
                <para>
                Exporting your asset information will give you a list of comma separated 
		values.  The first line of which will be the field names, and each subsequent 
		line a device.
                </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="chap8sect4" label="8.4">
                <title>Importing Asset Information</title>
                <para>
                This feature, by itself, is basically useless in it's current state.  The node id 
		must match for each device, and because of that, this information can not be passed 
		from one management station to another, nor could it even be used across installations, 
		unless you remapped the node ids.  Information could be exported from a management 
		station, imported into a spread sheet, then modified, exported back to a comma 
		separated list, and then re-imported back into the same management station from which 
		it was initially exported.  Or alternately the exported list could be modified by 
		an external script and then re-imported if for instance you would need to duplicate 
		information such as addresses for a large number of devices.
                </para>
		<para>
		Note that when re-importing information, the field names (the first line) should be left 
		out.  That is, if you export and save the resultant .csv file, pasting this file in the 
		import field would cause an error in the first line.  The field names are only there for 
		the sake of another spreadsheet/database program that could read them as field names.
		</para>
        </sect1>
</chapter>
